Hello, Arkadiusz Woźniak here, one of the voice actors from the 'History of Khorinis’ cast.
In this movie in the name of the SoulFire team I will show you and explain a few untold secrets and
stories from the original Gothic game, which you will see just in the 'History'.
Another attraction will be trivia’s and game secret that have not been unrevealed by NOBODY.
Every information in this movie are exhaustively researched
and confirmed by ex and current staff of Piranha Bytes'.
Film is mainly dedicated to people, who played in the Gothic saga many years ago
and they might not remember many plots and for the rest,
who did not follow minor or uncertain plot details.
Enjoy watching!
The Demon Hunters
In Gothic 2 files we can find two textures of armors
that does not appear in the game - indicated by abbrevation 'DHT'
Many modders, who could find this textures thought
that abrrevation 'DHT' means 'Dragon Hunter'
which was pointed by logic.
It means that they are old version of textures of the Dragon Hunters,
which were not used in the final version of the game.
Our statement was similar until we found and published screenshots of 3d models of these armors
Then Johnny from YouTube channel AHRN.eu - an author of the series 'Gothic in nutshell'
- wrote to Dark and Avallach, the coordinators of our project.
He told us (by learning about this from the one of Piranhas ex-employer
that in this case the abrevation of 'DHT' in fact means Demon Hunter!
The Demon Hunters had been a part of story of a project,
which was in development in second half of 2001.
It was a mysterious addon to Gothic 1, which was mentioned by Johnny and Archon
in the second part of the movie 'Gothic in nutschell'.
Piranha named him the 'Gothic Sequel' and project was independent continuation
of the Nameless Hero's story - just after the collapse of the magic barrier.
In big short - in chaos which has set in the world after banishing the Sleeper,
our Nameless Hero was forced to professional killing these demonic creatures.
Later the project had become canceled and Piranha Bytes focused on development Gothic 2,
using a number of resources and ideas created for the addon.
'Seekers' from Gothic 2 and model and texture of from the Night of the Raven
also came from this unreleased addon to the first Gothic.
A code for summoning this kind of scavengers is 'insert Scavenger_demon'
It appears that that kind of scavengers had been one of the demons in that sequel.
The Demon Hunters have just changed into the Dragon Hunters.
In the 'History of Khorinis' we will have a chance to meet those Demon Hunters a
s an independent mercenary guild, being paid by the mystery organisation.
Their armors (and all other armors from the addon to Gothic 1)
from the Piranha Bytes' materials will be reproduced by us - with the all details.
You can be sure about their quality.
In this way, we can combine our ideas in harmony with the
lore of Gothic perfectly, by making use of Piranha’s unused ideas!
PS: We also recreated the deleted guild of the Inquisitors,
which came from the same addon as well.
How many mages took part in the creation of the Barrier? Twelve or thirteen?
'Well, when we - the twelve magicians - created the Barrier back then,
our magic powers were directed and controlled by a thirteenth magician'
'A thirteenth magician? I thought there were only twelve!'
In order to make not confusion, I quote to us a fragment of an interview from the 3rd of April 2011
, when Mike Hoge – a story designer of Gothic 1 – gave an interview to Gothicz.net
Gothicz.net aksed: As we know, the Magic Barrier in Gothic 1
was created by twelve magicians plus Xardas
In the Colony we can find precisely the same count of them,
however the Fire Mage Milten
came into the Colony after the Barrier was created. So we are missing one Fire Mage.
It seems to me quite impossible, that you would overlook this disharmony.
So what happened to this unknown Mage?
Mike Hoge answered: The Magic Barrier was created by 12 magicians,
Xardas being one of them!!
When the Necromancer left the Old Camp,
there were only 5 mages
So they took Milten as an apprentice, when he was thrown
into the Colony after the Barrier had been created.
There is a dialogue in the game where one of the
mages gets the numbers wrong. I think it was Saturas...
I noticed that error, fixed it and some ex-team member
of mine "fixed" it back because he didn't understand the background.
There is no missing mage. The guy just messed it up!
It seems that case of magicians has been made clear
- there were twelve magicians. Let's proceed to next problem:
'This thirteenth magician was our leader. All this took place
before we were divided into the Circles of Fire and Water.'
The Circles of Water and Fire
In the next spoken dialogue Saturas claimed that division into the Circles of Fire and Water
have followed after the creation of the Barrier.
You need to know that it is the same LIE as idea about
existence of the thirteenth mage, botched by the same programmer!
In any case, he was FIRED from the team after the release of Gothic 1,
which proves that Piranhas didn't tolerate his insubordination.
Another, dispelling doubts proofs are information from the game.
In the scene from the intro of Gothic 1, which is placed during creation
of the Barrier we can see a Water Mage in hood. Most likely it was Saturas.
At the moment of throwing Nameless Hero we can meet the Archmage of Fire - Pyrokar.
Then in Gothic 2 we get to know about the Monastery of Innos with the history going back hundreds of years
We also get to know that Xardas was the member of the Hing Council of the Circle of Fire
as a prior of the Monastery before the creation of the Barrier,
and we read his notes in the hidden underground library
- which crosses the dialogue mistakes out expressly
The ultimate nail in his coffin are information from the sequel of the game.
And... that's it.
Prior to the creation of the barrier, the Fire and Water Mages
were just united and they cooperated under leadership of the one Archmage – Xardas.
The Circles of Water and Fire are only specializations connected with particular god.
Magicians help each other and share their knowledge.
Meanwhile, they stay in separate congregations.
It can be compared to the Dominican Order and the Franciscans Order
during the Middle Ages, which they do not like each other
though they responded to pope in common.
In this case we have actually have two gods,
but only one king whom the magicians serve - Rhobar II.
In theory, the Water Magicians participation in creating the Barrier is also motivated by the fact that Beliar’s armies
have achieved an advantage, becoming the biggest threat to the world.
CONCLUSION - there were twelve magicians creating the magic barriers,
Xardas was one of them and maigicians were divided into the Circles of Water and Fire.
Marshal Rigaldo
Have you yet remembered a letter from the intro of Gothic 1,
which was given to the Nameless Hero by Pyrokar?
In the current version it is not signed, however our main programmer
Avallach found many years ago, that the Piranha Bytes
had left hidden (but not erased from code) sign in scripts:
'Rigaldo, the King's Marshal'
Curious people can find this sign in the script of the letter without problems.
We are showing you the line of code on the screen.
From the sign it may result a new sense of
the letter for the Archmage of the Fire Circle.
We know that that marshal was one of the most important person on the court,
who as the first counselor and representative was responsible for negotiations between King and Gomez.
It would be a sin if we hadn't expanded this plot,
astounding not only player, but also the Piranha Bytes.
Marshal Rigaldo will appear in the 'History of Khorinis' in unexpected circumstances.
We don't let you down in this matter.
A true reason of the creation the barrier
Gothic 1 version
'To make it impossible for them to escape, the King sent out the best magicians
of the kingdom to create a magic barrier around the entire valley.'
In other words it is directly suggested, that it was a king's order
so we can interpret it in many ways.
The most sensible conclusion is: somebody could give a few propositions to solve the problem with
prisoners to the king, which one of them was chosen and finally the king gave the order.
Gothic 2 version
To do not causing confusion I just quote journals, notates and the Xardas'
almanac from the underground library from Gothic 2, which was found by the Nameless Hero:
‘I hope the dome may protect the ore from the menace of Beliar.
THE KING IS NAIVE enough to believe that we built the dome as protection against breakouts
Well, as long as such ruses enable us to fulfill our higher goals, let it be so.
I can only hope we have enough time left to prepare for the fight.
I will use all the power at my disposal to intervene in the impeding fight.'
'I am now certain that the building is the Halls of Irdorath.
They are located on an island quite near the harbor of Khorinis.
Beliar's interest in the ore mines is obvious...
There will be war, a war for the fate of the world.
I seem to be the only one capable of interpreting the signs.
All around me seem to ignore them.
The One will come, and his coming will herald the beginning of the war.
It is a war as old as time itself, but the end appears to be coming into view.
I will not stand idly by and watch as others take the fate of the world into their hands.'
After familiarizing with both versions the question is:
What was the point in the lying the king instead of
giving him the real reason of the creation the Barrier?
Totally nonsense, right?
Actually what is the difference when we even have two good reasons instead of one?
Events from Gothic 2 - the invasion of the Mine Valley by Beliar’s armies
confirmed that Xardas was right and that was exactly the target of enemy,
namely Orcs and another creatures under the leadership of the Dragons and Beliar.
Separating the King from the magic ore.
He delayed this invasion for almost ten years
Besides, the magic barrier which protects mines is perfect from the strategic point of view.
So why did Xardas and the Magicians lie to the King and maintain the true reason?
As far as we know, an idea of the creation the barrier
has just got many opposition at the King's court.
If Rhobar - being frightened by naysayers - had been known
a true purpose of the creation the barrier,
he would have only sent an army to protect (which as we know from the future event
it could not stop the Orcs) - instead of separating it from the world.
Problem with fugitives - also problems with guarding prisoners - and complaints from local lords
about these events were a perfect pretext and opportunity to realize the plan made by Xardas.
A subject of our addon make that our PRIORITY was to explain this matter to players.
You will get to know about this background of events during the game.
An intensification of the law some time before the creation of the barrier
‘… and every meant guilty of a crime no matter how insignificant was forced to work in the ore mines of Khorinis’
From the words above we can see, that the law has been stiffen
some time before the creation of the barrier – so during the action of our addon.
Before that only the worst convicts and recidivist were sent to the Colony.
Many of the hired miners also worked there.
After the beginning of the second Orcish conquest of Myrthana,
when the royal army had begun losing, the King who became desperate and hard-pressed
made a decision that every criminal no matter how
insignificant was his crime must be forced to work in the mines,
in order to receive bigger and bigger transports of the ore.
During the action of the ‘History’ you will be witnesses how the new law is going into effect
which resulted from the dramatic situation that the Kingdom was affected.
In the addon you will also see that it is going to gather the first and bloody toll.
Remember - you mustn’t commit a crime on Vaduz!
The LORE locations from the world of Myrthana
During the action of the 'History of Khorinis'
you will hear about many places and location from the world of Myrthana.
More importantly - there will be places already
mentioned in the LORE of first two parts of Gothic saga!
In order to make things clear we quote them all,
and we will tell who or where did these places mention.
The Southern Isles is a place of warm and exotic climate.
In Gothic 2 we can obtain Red tear-pepper
from the Southern Isles.
Randolph - a worker on the Akil's Farm also came from that place.
'You're not from around here, right?
I come from the Southern Isles,
At some point they said they needed people in Khorinis, because of that magic ore.
But when I got there, they had this huge barrier in place.
And I dind't want to go in there. So I started working in the harbor.'
We also know, that Lord Dominique had fought on the Southern Islands, bearing the Shield of Fire
- which was finally attached to the wall in the Monastery of Fire on the Khorinis island.
'Tell me about the Shield
The Shield of Fire was borne by Dominique in the battle on the Southern Isles.
But the power of this shield is never to be wielded again – therefore, we have nailed it to the wall.’
The last important information is a book called ‘Southern Defense Art'.
It provides us an information about one-hand fighting.
We can buy it from merchant Lutero in the upper city of Khorinis
Besides rules of fight we also get to know by reading that:
‘In the hot climate of his home…’
Attention! It is not uncerain if the authors of
book tell us about Southerners from the Southern Isles,
because it could be Varrant as well.
It is possible that book refers to Southerners in general way
namely inhabitants of both regions.
We are not sure, but the climate of both regions is similar
so we can consider this version as correct.
The Eestern Archipelago is a group of isles closed to each other,
placed on the east of mainland and Khorinis.
Many hard battles with the Orcs had been fought there,
including the Navy of both sides.
During the action of Gothic 2 Mario - being a witness of an
ultimate defeat of the Royal Navy - had fought there.
'I am... I was a leutenant with the royal navy.'
I served as a marine on the 'King Rhobar' and the ‘Pride of Myrthana’.
In the Battle of the Eastern Archipelago
I single-handedly sent a dozen Orcs back to Beliar’s realm.
Unfortunately, there were too few of us after
our flagship sank, so we were forced to retreat.’
Varrant is a region on the mainland with the access to sea,
with the climate similar the Middle East or Jharkendar.
We can find there both oasis and deserts, steppes and swamps.
We heard about it in Gothic 1 for the first time,
in a two-tome book called ‘the Battle of Varrant’.
There it was a place that Rhobar and General Lee achieved
a success by defeating the army of Varrant.
From the second tome of book we know, that Lee
lured heavy cavalry led by general Lukkor into swamps.
The enemy cavalry hadn’t a chance on wetlands, so they became defeated.
From books we also know that Varrant had own sea ports.
Feros – the Dragon Hunter – probably came from the Varrant as well.
‘Where do you come from?
From the Mainland.
My people and I fled here.
The situation there is getting worse. The Orcs leave nothing but
burned-out villages behind.
The King has lost control of his realm.
Where are your people now?
I left them.
They thought they could take everything they wanted, even if it doesn’t
belong to them. Count me out.’
Laran is a region, from which a scholar Barthos came.
An author of books ‘A Gift from the Gods’ and
‘The Secrets of Magic’ which appeared in the first Gothic.
Archolos is a mountainous region. On its slopes we
can find the best grapes for wine throughout Myrthana.
This place is mentioned in the book ‘Recipes – Volume II’,
which can be found in the chest in Snaf’s house in Gothic 1.
The Northern Plains is a dry steppes located on the mainlaind.
They were mentioned in the first official comic – being
sold during the release of Gothic 1 in Germany.
Prior to action in Gothic 1 there had been a battlefield between the Orcs and humans.
There was a huge stronghold too.
Then, prior to the creation of the magic Barrier, those grounds
had been likely a place of bloody battles with the Orcs.
Those grounds can be seen on the intro of Gothic 1 as well.
Sendar is an another place mentioned in Gothic: Der Comic
- a comic book in the canon of Gothic.
It is the place from which Milten came.
The old passage
Many of you probably associate THIS place next to the Old Mine.
In the original Gothic a road went into rock in a weird way
- furthermore, this rock was a vertical, carelessly made wall.
Besides, the mountain has been 'cut out' in unnatural way.
What's going on here?
From over a year we can see in the Internet a screenshot
from the gameplay provided to german game press,
on which that place can be seen on the map of the Colony.
With the kindness of a certain person, Avallach received an insight
into THE SAME version of game, which appeared in this gameplay.
It is a version 1.01d from november 2000.
With this we can show you this map in perfect quality.
We can see a terrain and road deleted
from the original model of the world.
From Johnny from AHRN we've got an interesting
screen from beginning of 2000,
on which a road and fragment of a palisade can be seen
- in the place where in G1 we could see only wall.
Then on another screenshots from 1999 that deleted
terrain can be seen from other perspectives.
Time for conclusions.
Now hold up!
IN FACT THERE WAS AN EXIT PASSAGE FROM THE MINE VALLEY!
On a comparative screenshot made by Avallach
can be seen that prisoners come into the valley
through the old, true passage
and on both screenshots the Old Mine is placed on the left side.
As you can see in order to set a frame from the intro
on the map of Gothic 1 we had to leave outside the terrain.
Moreover it appears, that the castle in the centre of the Colony
has been elevated with the aim of creating the intro and
for better visibility and cinematic effect.
Besides, next proof is the fact that two wide roads lead
to deleted passage – whence one of them passed the Old Mine.
The deleted terrain and road from the castle lead in that way.
Moreover, both passages are directed exactly in the same direction
to the north of Khorinis
But why has the Piranha’s decided on deleting this part of passage and closing him with a mere rock?
It is quite simple: being so close to the release of game,
they hadn’t much time to make a final touches on that passage.
The same did also with underground city of the Orcs,
or the Collapsed Mine - their meshes can be found in the files of game.
Many of things had been deleted by Piranha before the release,
and if the Passage hadn’t had no plot reason to be there
because according to the intro prisoners were thrown
behind the Barrier from the slope next to the Collapsed Mine,
then it would have been no need to finish it.
Imagine also that it would be the ONLY one place in the game,
where the important road will be intersected by the magic barier.
For sure it could bring new technical problems.
In the ‘History of Khorinis’ we are reconstructing this passage in order to preserve
the sense and logic in ore transport. It is also reconstructed to bridge the gap made by the Piranha Bytes.
And how do we explain that after the creation of the barrier the passage has been secluded by rocks?
You shall see during the game.
A map of Khorinis in the ‘History’
Because of a fact that in the Internet we can see a lot of dumb maps,
which show you the Island of Khorinis in the shape of THE TERRAIN from Gothic 2,
we want to give you a true look on it.
Those imitations, which were mentioned before,
override an existence of the Mine Valley in the South
and Jharkendar beyond the mountains in the Northeast
We are informed about these directions
from the NPC’s from Gothic 2 and its addon.
Taking into consideration these three parts
of the island and their situation, the island should got this shape.
In our vision the island – made by Avallach – looks like this.
Of course the Jharkendar is consciously marked as the ‘Northern Wastelands’,
because an inhabitants of the Khorinis have lived in the conviction,
that those terrain are high and inaccessible mountain massifs.
The existence of Jharkendar is only known to the Pirates
and later also to the Eremite and the Master Builders.
Lord Tymorisin’s Castle and Bermar’s Fortress
For those, who forgot and they will be playing in
the second part of the ‘History’, which is placed on Khorinis,
we want to remind that liege lords, who had lived in
dominions in the Mine Valley before the creation of the Magic Barrier
were Burgrave Bergmar and Lord Tymorisin.
We can meet the Burgrave for the first time when we visit the Montane Fortress
with Lester in order to find the freehold of that stronghold.
We hear first mentions from Lester:
‘This document you're looking for... what is it?
Many years ago, the lord of this area lived in this mountain fort.
He controlled the land and the mines.
Like any other aristocrat, he had, of course, a document to verify his tenure.’
And the rest we can read in the document, finding out about details of the owner of the Fortress,
Bergmar – and his liege – Lord Tymorisin, who ruled over the Mine Valley
as a liege lord from his castle in the centre of the valley.
His castle will have undamaged tower like in the intro of Gothic 1.
Each of them had got profits from mines. But which mines had they controlled?
Did Xardas urge them to acceptance of creating the barrier?
And why did burgrave Bergmar decide to sell his own
stronghold to the mysterious buyer and the Church of Innos?
You will find out in the ‘History of Khorinis’.
The Orcs in the Mine Valley?
Many of you are wondering how it was possible that the Orcs had
been everywhere in the Colony since the creation of the Barrier?
An answer to a question is quite simple.
The first proof is a location of bargrave Begmar’s Montane Fortress.
In Gothic 1 it is placed deeply on the terrain under the Orcs control
Then we hear from Lester that before the the creation of the Barrier,
Burgrave and his retinue had managed an extraction in some mines,
which proves that in their times, the Mine Valley
had been completely controlled by humans.
During conversation with Ur-Shak in Gothic 2 we
get to know that some part of the Orcs comes to the valley with ships
,but others also come from the Southern Mountains.
It means that the Orcs had their own camps in those mountains.
‘Why are there suddenly so many of you?
Orcs come from mountains, but others come with ships and make big fence.
From our studies and from different sources (including those from Piranha)
we have come to conclusion that:
The Orcs had already been defeated in the Mine Valley
long since before Bergmar and Tymorisin.
Overwhelmed by strength of the enemy, they took shelter
in the Southern Mountains and in the city on the southern outskirts of the valley.
On that outskirts they were secluded from the humans by deep lake and forest.
Because the stone bridge was built later, nobody knew about existence
of Orcish city placed so close to the human dominion.
Indiviudal Orcs – being probably the hunters are seen very rarely.
The rulers of the Valley suspect that
many of them live hiding in the mountains,
but because of more important matters they
do not have much time, resources and more importantly
eagerness to catch them. They are no particular threat to them.
After the creation of the barrier, which got out of control,
the Orcs in rage decided to blow the whistle on hidden life.
By abandoning their own hideouts they
took sizeable areas in the south of the valley.
A final complement of this plan were events from Gothic 2, when the Orcs from the mountains
came out to the valley with the help to their kind by taking control on whole island
Xardas' robes
Many of you are wondering why we have decided to keep
a very similar shape of Xardas’ robes as the Archmage of Fire
to this one known from Gothic 1 or 2,
so from the times we he has already been the Necromancer.
We did this due to very prosaic, but also very important reason.
Having regard to fact that Xardas was a different person ten years ago,
we didn’t want to divest him of charisma or personality.
Taking into consideration the fact that he was the highest and the most powerful magician
of the Circle of Fire throughout the Kingdom, we decided
that he deserves for more characteristic and different than others robe,
which also emphasizes his function and position.
A solution with the ‘old-new’ Archmage of the Fire robe -
which it colors will be replaced into much darker by Xardas -
was considered by us as the best one.
And Xardas will still remain as an old fogey.
No references to Gothic 3
As you all know, Arcania and Forsaken Gods
do not exist for the plot of our addon.
However, after many discussions we came to more revolutionary conclusion,
to say, that references to Gothic 3 should be
reduced to zero, as if this part also did not exist.
WE DO NOT MEAN to fight with the Piranha Bytes’ idea but we think we can't preserve
something which has distorted our imagination about appearance, history and the world of this glorious game.
That's why we preserve only information from the first Gothic, second and the Night of the Raven
by developing all threads which told us about the Kingdom as the power
and the something more interesting and stunning than we saw in Gothic 3.
The current shape of Gothic 3 may result from desire to adapt for the American market,
or pressure from publisher, or because of poor idea of this game.
That’s why we ask you to treat the ‘History of Khorinis’ as a part, which was released in harmony
with the canon of Gothic 1, 2 and the Night of the Raven without knowledge about lore and mainland from Gothic 3
On our part you can expect from us the same.
And that's it!
Thank you for watching! If you are interested in more amount of unknown
information from Gothic, let us know in comment section.
We also encourage to subscribing the channel,
because we are preparing for you many videos not only
from the world of the 'History of Khorinis', but also voice-over production,
interviews with actors from our addon and videos similar to this one.
Take care yourself, and may Innos watch over you always!
Idea and realisation – Piotr ‘Dark’ Czołnkowski and Adam ‘Avallach’ Gołębiowski
Video and editing: Radosław ‘Revo’ Rak
Initial montaże: Doktor Borginson
Substantive support: Jan ‘Johnny’ Baryła
Narrator: Arkadisz 'Arkadikuss' Woźniak
English subtitles: Bartosz ‘Kereth’ Biały based on polish subitles made by Szymon ‘Szmyk’ Żak